<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The theater of Iaponia's constancy in which an hundred and eighteene glorious martyrs suffered death for Christ, in the yeare of our Lord 1622. Also, a briefe relation of the many, and wonderfull miracles, it hath pleased God lately to worke, by the merits and intercession of S. Ignatius, founder of the Society of Iesus, at Munebrega a towne in Spayne, in the moneths of Aprill and May, of the yeare 1623. Both faithfully translated out of Spanish originalls, lately printed at Madrid.</title>
            <title>Teatro de la constancia japonesa.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842299</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842299</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 742:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The theater of Iaponia's constancy in which an hundred and eighteene glorious martyrs suffered death for Christ, in the yeare of our Lord 1622. Also, a briefe relation of the many, and wonderfull miracles, it hath pleased God lately to worke, by the merits and intercession of S. Ignatius, founder of the Society of Iesus, at Munebrega a towne in Spayne, in the moneths of Aprill and May, of the yeare 1623. Both faithfully translated out of Spanish originalls, lately printed at Madrid.</title>
                  <title>Teatro de la constancia japonesa.</title>
                  <author>Badduley, William, b. 1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press] Permissu Superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXIIII. [1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by William Badduley alias Lee, of: Teatro de la constancia japonesa.</note>
                  <note>Includes "Saint Ignatius his triumph", also translated by William Lee.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ignatius, --  of Loyola, Saint, 1491-1556 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Martyrs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Miracles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6944:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE THEATER Of Iaponia's Conſtancy: IN WHICH <hi>An</hi> Hundred <hi>&amp;</hi> Eighteene <hi>Glorious Martyrs ſuffered Death for Chriſt, in the yeare of our Lord</hi> 1622. ALSO A briefe Relation of the many, and wonderfull Miracles, it hath pleaſed God lately to worke, by the Merits and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of S. IGNATIVS, Founder of the Society of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, at <hi>Munebrega</hi> a Towne in <hi>Spayne,</hi> in the Moneths of Aprill and May, of the yeare 1623. <hi>Both faithfully Tranſlated out of the Spanish Originalls, lately printed at Madrid.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of the English College at Saint-Omer, featuring the seal of the Jesuites or Society of Jesus, a sunburst containing a cross over the letters IHS over three nails</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>IHS</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <q>Mirabilis Deus in Sanctis ſuis. <bibl>Pſal. <hi>67.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Permiſſu Superiorum, M.DC.XXIIII.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:6944:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6944:2"/>
            <head>THE THEATER OF IAPONIA'S CONSTANCY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE cauſe of the enſuing ſo ſtrange and cruell Martyrdomes, ſuch as were neuer heard of in the Kingdom of <hi>Iaponia,</hi> ſince the Perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians there began, was this as followeth.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Emperour of <hi>Iaponia</hi> ſome yeares paſt, had forbidden, by Proclamation throughout all the Prouinces of that Kingdome, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine of death, that no Sayler or Mariner ſhould bring any Chriſtian Religious man into <hi>Iaponia;</hi> which was a thing very eaſy to be done, in regard that <hi>Manila</hi> the chiefe Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Philippine</hi> Ilands is ſo neare, and where there is ſo great trafficke betweene the <hi>Spanyards</hi> and <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians:</hi> Notwithſtanding ſome there were both Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and Catholike Marriners, who ſtyrred vp with zeale of Gods Honour, not regarding the threats and penaltyes of the lawes, did bring at ſundry tymes from <hi>Manila</hi> into <hi>Iaponia,</hi> many Religious men, in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6944:3"/> ſecular apparell, to cultiuate and manure that new-planted Vineyard of this new-found Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the ſayd Marriners there was one more famous the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt, Captayne of a ſhip, called <hi>Ioachim,</hi> who as he ſayled from <hi>Manila</hi> towards <hi>Iaponia,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him two very Reuerend Religious men, the one wherof was called Father <hi>Pedro de Zuniga</hi> of the Order of <hi>S. Auſten,</hi> and the other, Father <hi>Lewis de Flores</hi> of the Order of <hi>S. Dominicke,</hi> whome he could not tranſport ſo ſecretly, but they were betrayed by certayne <hi>Hollande s,</hi> who euen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very ſhoare of <hi>Iaponia,</hi> inuaded and robbed <hi>Ioachims</hi> ſhip, and alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed him before the Emperours Officers, for brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the ſayd Religious men with him into <hi>Iaponia,</hi> contrary to the Emperours Proclamation: And for this cauſe was <hi>Ioachim</hi> preſently caſt into priſon at <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum,</hi> togeather with the ſayd two Fathers, and all the other Marriners that were Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>There was at that tyme in the ſame Citty reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding another Religious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the order of <hi>S. Dominick</hi> who went about to deliuer the foreſayd Father <hi>Lewis</hi> out of priſon; which indeed he had almoſt effected, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with the deliuery of many more Chriſtians that were in the ſame Priſon; but becauſe he could not breake open the priſon doores without great noyſe, nor bring to paſſe what he had determined, with that ſecrecy he deſired, his plot was ſoone diſcouered, and all the Priſoners brought backe againe into priſon.</p>
            <p>When the Emperour heard of this, he tooke the matter ſo heynouſly, and was ſo inraged againſt the Chriſtians, aſwell in regard of the new comming of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6944:3"/> thoſe Religious men into his Kingdome, to preach the Chriſtian fayth, as alſo, becauſe they had broken his Maieſties priſon; that without delay, he comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Gouernour of <hi>Nangaſachi</hi> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to repayre to <hi>Firandum,</hi> and there put to death firſt of all <hi>Ioachim</hi> the Captayne, and afterwards the two Religious men that he brought with him, as alſo all the other Marriners, that were Chriſtians. Moreouer he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that all other Religious men, whether they were of <hi>Europe,</hi> or of <hi>Iaponia</hi> who were impriſoned in diuers Cittyes ſhould be put to death. And the like pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment he charged to be inflicted vpon all Widows, and Orphanes, whoſe Husbands, or Parents had in the former Perſecution of late yeares, ſuffered death for the fayth of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Gouernour with all ſpeed, at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours commaundment, came to <hi>Firandum,</hi> where cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for the priſoners, he began to examine and aske them many queſtions; as, whether they were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? From whence they came? Of what Nation they were? And when, and where they were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed? Nor he did forget, now and then to exhort them to renounce their Fayth, promiſing them their liues, if they would ſo do; &amp; affirming that he had full power and Commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Emperour, for what he promiſed.</p>
            <p>But to this laſt, one and the ſelfe ſame moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reply was made by all; That nothing in the world ſhould cauſe them deny their fayth, nor breake the promiſe they had made to IESVS CHRIST in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Vpon which anſwere and firme reſolution, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6944:4"/> Gouernour preſently pronounced ſentence, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Captayne <hi>Ioachim,</hi> and the two Religious Fathers <hi>Pedro de Zuniga</hi> the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Friar, and Father <hi>Lewis de Flores</hi> the Dominican, to be burned aliue, &amp; the reſt of the Marriners, who were twelue in number, to be beheaded.</p>
            <p>Now theſe holy Confeſſours of IESVS CHRIST hauing receaued this doom, the more to increaſe their ioy and aſſurance of dying for Chriſts ſake, demanded of the Gouernour, for what cauſe he adiudged them to death? And they receiued this anſwere in very plaine tearmes: to wit, that the Religious men muſt dye, becauſe they had againſt the Emperours decree, entred into <hi>Iaponia</hi> to preach the law of Chriſt; and the reſt for that they had brought the ſaid Preachers into the Countrey to that end. Which plaine declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was an exceeding ioy and Iubily of heart vnto them all, when they ſaw themſelues condemned to death for the fayth, and loue of IESVS CHRIST.</p>
            <p>The place appointed for the execution, was out of the Citty of <hi>Firandum,</hi> where there was a faire and large plot of ground, like vnto an Amphitheater, all incloſed round with woodden rayles. Hither were the holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſours brought forth of the Citty, with infinite multitudes of people, and the three foremoſt placed ech one at a pillar, or ſtake, whereunto they were bound, with great aboundance of fagots, and wood layd round about them. But before the fire was kindled, the other twelue Marriners heads were ſtroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off within the foreſaid place, before the eyes of the Holy Confeſſours, that ſtood now ready at the ſtake
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6944:4"/> to be burned.</p>
            <p>Heere now the good Captayne <hi>Ioachim</hi> made knowne the force of Chriſtian Eloquence, being not only permitted, but alſo commanded by the ſayd two Religious Fathers his Companions (who by reaſon of the ſhort tyme of their abode in <hi>Iaponia,</hi> had not yet learned the language of that countrey) to profeſſe the fayth of Chriſt in the name of all the reſt. Of whome, ſuch as did both ſee and heare him, do affirme, that he ſeemed rather to ſpeake like an Apoſtle, then an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Preacher, much leſſe a poore Marriner; ſuch was the feruour, ſuch the courage wherewith he preached IESVS CHRIST, in the very middeſt of the fyre and ſmoke. And by how much more the barbarous Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils endeauoured aſwell by often interrupting him, as by threats, to make him hold his peace; ſo much the more did he cry out, and ſay, that it was meet he ſhould rather obey God then Man. Neyther, can I be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied (ſayd he) by your threatninges: for what more cruell, or more grieuous torment can you deuiſe, then that which I now indure in burning heere aliue? And this he ſaid out of the middeſt of the burning fire, as if it had bene out of a flaming pulpit, with an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feruour of ſpirit, being indeed inflamed with the loue of IESVS CHRIST. Nor did he leaue darting out ſuch fiery words, vntill himſelfe, togeather with his two moſt bleſſed Companions, with wonderfull conſtancy ended their liues, and that in ſo quiet a manner, as if they had been altogeather immoueable, and wrapt in heauenly contemplation.</p>
            <p>This firſt Pageant was repreſented vpon the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6944:5"/> one and twentith day of Auguſt, in the yeare of our Lord 1622. in preſence of an infinite number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who by continuall acclamations and crying out, and calling vpon God to aſſiſt them, endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all meanes poſſible to encourage the holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs to ſuffer death patiently, for the loue of IESVS CHRIST.</p>
            <p>The Executioners, as ſoone as they perceyued that the Martyrs were dead, went, and expoſed the heads of thoſe which they had firſt ſtroken of, vpon a very high Table, to the greater feare, and terrour of all that ſhould behold them. But the bodyes, aſwell of thoſe that were beheaded, as of thoſe that were bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they layd them all vpon a heape togeather, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the place of execution, well guarded round about with railes of wood, as alſo with ſouldiers, vntill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order were giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ſhould be done with them.</p>
            <p>The concourſe of the people that came thither both night and day to worſhip thoſe Holy Reliques, was wonderfull; notwithſtanding the many and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous blowes, yea and wounds which they receyued of the ſouldiers who were commanded there to watch, that no Chriſtian ſhould take away any of the ſame. But yet all they could do, was not inough to preuaile againſt the good deſires of the Chriſtians, but that ſome of the more principall ſort, what by their owne Induſtry, and what by bribing of the ſouldiers, with pious deceyt ſtole away ſome of the bodyes. Amongſt which they had a particular care to take away the whole body of Father <hi>Pedro de Zuniga,</hi> with intention to conuay it firſt to the Citty of <hi>Manila,</hi> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6944:5"/> to ſend it into <hi>Spaine,</hi> where the Honour of ſo worthy a death, and the ornaments of ſo glorious a Triumph, due not only to the excellency of his Vertue and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but alſo to the Nobility of his bloud and birth (his Father being Marqueſſe of <hi>Manrique,</hi> &amp; ſometymes Viceroy of <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> or new <hi>Spaine</hi>) are expected to be celebrated with all due Reuerence and Solemnity.</p>
            <p>The Gouernour of <hi>Nangaſachi,</hi> after he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed the crowne of Martyrdome vpon theſe victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Champions, ſent his Officers to <hi>Omura</hi> to fetch thoſe other Chriſtians, of whome we made mention before, who lay there in priſon, deſiring and longing for nothing ſo much as to ſee that happy houre, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they might come to ſhed their bloud for the loue of IESVS Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Behold now heere, I beſeech you (Gentle Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators) behold heere a conflict, nay rather an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Combate, and ſuch a Combate as the like was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene before in all <hi>Iaponia.</hi> Fiue and fifty valiant Champions of IESVS Chriſt, vpon one and the ſelfe ſame day, obteined the victorious Palme of martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in manner as followeth.</p>
            <p>Of theſe moſt happy Warryours of Chriſt, fiue &amp; twenty were taken out of priſon at <hi>Omura,</hi> wherin, though ſome longer then others, yet all in generall, as young ſouldiers they had bene trayned vp in this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Fencing-Schoole, with ſo hard, and miſerable a vſage, as barbarous Heathens are accuſtomed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine ſuch gueſts withall. For, there was made vnder the ground, a moſt horrible and filthy Caue, ſcarce large inough for twelue ordinary matt-beds of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6944:6"/> bulruſhes, to lye one by another. Heere ſometimes thirty priſoners, ſometimes more, three and three to a matte of eight palmes long, and three in breadth, were conſtrained to lodge both night and day, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hauing ſo much as one foote of roome more to ſtir vp and downe in: &amp; which is more (and of it ſelf alone had bene inough to diſpatch them all in ſhort tyme) in the very ſame roome, they were to giue place vnto the neceſſity of nature. And as for their dyet, the daily pittance allowed them, was a little diſh of blacke Ryce, with a few broyled Pilchards, or as it chanced now and then a ſuppe of broth, wherein Radiſh lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues had bene boyled.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, whileſt the Officers were taking theſe couragious Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pions out of the foreſaid miſerable dungeon, to be conueyed to the place of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, the Gouernour called for thirty men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men alſo out of the priſon of <hi>Nangaſachi,</hi> whome he determined to put to death togeather, with thoſe that were to come from <hi>Omura.</hi> And when he had giuen ſentence of death againſt them, commanding that the ſame ſhould be put in execution the next day, he ſent them backe againe vnto priſon: who albeit they went chayned all togeather, like malefactours, worthy to dye for moſt notorious crymes; yet they departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iudgment ſeat with great Ioy and Iubily of heart, euery one holding vp a Crucifix, or other Croſſe in his hand, as high as he could, in ſigne of Tryumph.</p>
            <p>The troupe of couragious Women marched firſt; amongſt whome one more eminent, as Captayne, went before the reſt, with a banner of Chriſt IESVS
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6944:6"/> crucifyed diſplayed in her hands. After her followed all the reſt in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of proceſſion, ſounding forth the prayſes of Almighty God, with all honour, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, and contempt of the Idols with all ſcorne and reproach: wherof many of the woman lifted vp in their armes towards Heauen, their little ſucking Chriſtian Babes, as Sacrifices ready to be offred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God together with themſelues.</p>
            <p>After the women followed the vndaunted band of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, putting likewiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in ſuch order of proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that affoarded a moſt worthy &amp; pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eyes of God, &amp; to all the Chriſtians that beheld the ſame; who not contented with the only beholding therof, but inflamed with an holy emulation of their hapines, went alſo in great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; following their ſteps with great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; deuotion.</p>
            <p>Not long after this, entred into the Citty the foreſaid Priſoners that were ſent for from <hi>Omura,</hi> in number fiue and twenty, amongſt whome one and twenty were Religious men of diuers Orders: Whom when the Chriſtians of <hi>Nangaſachi</hi> beheld, what flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made they (thinke you) to come to ſee, and to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute them? Who is able to recount with what teares and ſighes euery one now entertained his ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by whome he had bene baptized, and regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſt IESVS? Who can expreſſe with what weeping and lamentation they deplored their owne moſt lamentable caſe, that theſe their ſpirituall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Tutours, and Maiſters, ſhould now be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of life, by whoſe meanes the life of grace had not only bene ſo long nouriſhed and conſerued, but euen
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6944:7"/> firſt of all infuſed into their ſoules? In the meane tyme, the ioyfull Fathers ceaſed not to comfort their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted children, bidding them be of good comfort; &amp; encouraging them to put their truſt in the Fatherly protection of Almighty God; aſſuring them that his Infinite Goodnes would neuer let them want other Fathers and Maiſters to nouriſh, and increaſe their good deſires. And ſo finally exhorting, &amp; animating them to perſeuere conſtantly in the ſincere and true fayth of IESVS Chriſt, euen vntill death, they tooke their laſt farewells.</p>
            <p>Being now come vnto the place of execution, the Officers aſſigned euery one a pillar or ſtake, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he was to be burned; which euery one of the holy Prieſts, before they were bound vnto them, falling downe vpon his knees, with great reuerence imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and ſaluted with a thouſand kiſſes: The like alſo did the lay Religious Brothers, being moued therunto by the pious example of the Prieſts. The ſight wherof was a cauſe of great admiration to the Beholders, and ſtirred vp in the harts of many ſo great feeling of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, that they could not refraine from teares.</p>
            <p>In this meane tyme, whileſt thoſe thirty priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which (as before we recounted) had bene ſent backe with their ſentence of death to the priſon, in the ſame Citty, were coming towards the ſame place of execution; the officers were buſied in binding to their ſeuerall pillars the fiue and twenty before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, all whome they bound but very looſely in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der following.</p>
            <p>Vnto the foure firſt pillars were bound foure Men,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6944:7"/> condemned for no other crime, but only becauſe they had ſometimes entertained and lodged in their houſes with great charity ſome of the ſayd Religious Fathers. Next vnto theſe ſtood the one and twenty Religious men, ſome of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Iaponia.</hi> The firſt place amongſt theſe, was allotted to the Reuerend Father <hi>Charles Spinola,</hi> an Italian Prieſt of the Society of IESVS, borne in <hi>Genua,</hi> and deſcended of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed Bloud and Family of the <hi>Spinola's,</hi> greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced and accounted of amongſt all men, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Birth, but much more in regard of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Vertue, his rare parts, and ſingular endowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts both of mind and body; as alſo for his exceſſiue and continuall labours &amp; paines, employed in cultiuating the vineyard of Chriſt IESVS in <hi>Iaponia,</hi> ſo far from his Natiue Country, which he, and all the reſt of thoſe who were of Europe, had forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the loue of God, to gaine ſoules in <hi>India.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After Father <hi>Spinola,</hi> followed the Reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Fa. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus Ferrerius</hi> of the order of <hi>S. Dominicke;</hi> Fa. <hi>Ioſeph de S. Iacintho</hi> of the ſame Order; Fa. <hi>Iacinthus,</hi> alſo of the ſame. Then followed Father <hi>Sebaſtian Quimura</hi> of the Society of IESVS, a Cittizen of <hi>Firandum</hi> borne in <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponia,</hi> who had liued there thirty yeares in the Society of IESVS, of which he had bene Prieſt for the ſpace of twenty; being himſelf the firſt <hi>Iaponian</hi> that euer tooke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the holy Order of Prieſthood, wherin he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed himſelfe a moſt worthy labourer in the vineyard of his Country, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> endowed with ſingular Vertues, and an excellent Preacher in the Iaponian language.</p>
            <p>Then followed the Reuerend Father <hi>Peter de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uila</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6944:8"/> of the order of <hi>S. Francis;</hi> Father <hi>Richard de S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> of the ſame Order; Father <hi>Alfonſus de Mena</hi> of the order of <hi>S. Dominicke;</hi> Father <hi>Francis de Morales</hi> of the ſame.</p>
            <p>They that were not Prieſts, were placed in this order: <hi>Vincentius,</hi> a Religious Brother of the order of <hi>Saint Francis</hi> borne in <hi>Europe: Anthony Fugia</hi> a Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, of the Society of IESVS: <hi>Gonſaluus Fuſay</hi> of the ſame Society and Countrey: <hi>Petrus Zampo</hi> of the ſame both religion and Countrey: <hi>Michael Iaponenſis</hi> of the ſame Order. After theſe againe followed foure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the order of <hi>S. Dominicke:</hi> And laſt of all were brought three of the Society of IESVS borne in <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> to wit <hi>Thomas Acaſgin, Ludouicus Cauarato,</hi> who were likewiſe bound to their pillars, and <hi>Iohn Chacoco,</hi> who alone amongſt thoſe fiue and twenty that were condemned to the fire, for want of a pillar whereat to be burned, was beheaded preſently; and firſt of all obtayned the crowne of Martyrdome by the ſword.</p>
            <p>So as to reckon them ouer againe there were of ſecular men Foure, that were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned for receiuing of the Religious Fathers into their houſes, Nine reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men of the order of <hi>S. Dominicke,</hi> Three of Saint Francis, and Nine of the Society of IESVS, all which being put together, do make the full number of fiue and twenty Crowned-Martyrs. The Executioners had ſcarce made an end of placing and binding theſe vnto their pillars, when behold that other new troupe of thirty glorious Confeſſours which were condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be beheaded, were brought to the ſame place, who as ſoone as they ſaw the religious men, they fell
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6944:8"/> ſodainly to imbracing, and ſaluting them with many teares and ſighes.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt, a certaine Matrone called <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella Fernandez,</hi> came running to the pillar wherunto Father <hi>Charles Spinola</hi> was bound, to giue him the laſt farewell. She was the wydow of a moſt noble Martyr who for hauing entertained the ſaid Father in his houſe had vnder gone a glorious death. She had a little child called <hi>Ignatius,</hi> ſcarce fiue yeares old, whom ſhe moſt deerely and tenderly loued. When ſhe was euen now ready to lay hold vpon the pillar, and Father <hi>Charles</hi> ready to ſalute her, he cryed out vnto her, <hi>ô Iſabella, Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella, vbi eſt tuus Ignatiolus? vbi est? vbi eſt, inquam, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liolus tuus?</hi> Where is your little <hi>Ignatius?</hi> where is, I ſay, your little Sonne? <hi>Iſabella</hi> hearing this, as ſhe had her hart all inflamed and ſet on fire, and to the end ſhe might make anſwere no leſſe by deedes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by words, made no more a doe, but ſtraight fetching forth her little One from amongſt the throng of people, tooke him in her armes, and lifting him vp towards Heauen, preſented him before the Father, ſaying: Behold heere (my deareſt Father) behold my little Sonne; behold heere I bring you my little <hi>Ignatius;</hi> I offer you my little ſonne, that he may be ſacrificed vnto God, and become a martyr, togeather with his mother, in this your Company.</p>
            <p>When Father <hi>Charles</hi> ſaw, and heard the Mother vtter ſuch reſolute ſpeaches, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning her little ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, it is incredible what comfort, and ſpirituall ioy he conceiued in his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Now approached the happy houre ſo much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6944:9"/> for of all this couragious Troupe: now was the fuell all ſet ready round about the pillars; but before the fire was put vnto it, the Executioners, with moſt barbarous cruelty, cut off the heads of thoſe thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men and women, as alſo of twelue young children, the eldeſt whereof was not yet full ten yeares old. And when it was demanded of them, Why they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed theſe before they had burned the others, that came firſt to the ſtake? They anſwered, they did it, to terrify and diſanimate them, that they might haue little courage to vndergoe the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the fire. And to the end they might better accompliſh what they did pretend, they tooke vp the heads of thoſe whome they had ſlaine, yet warme, and all-imbrued with their owne innocent bloud, and bowled, &amp; tumbled them vp and downe before their eyes.</p>
            <p>But when they ſaw that the holy Confeſſours could not be daunted, or diſcomfited with this, they kindled the fire. The fuell now, which on euery ſide enuironed the fiue and twenty Holy Martyrs, began indeed to flame, and burne vehemently: But (as many with particuler diligence obſerued) there was a great ſpace left betwixt the fire, and the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men; and as ſome, that were more curious then others, and tooke the meaſure of it, ſay it was no leſſe then three yards diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them on euery ſide. And this was alſo done of ſet purpoſe, that they might be tormented &amp; conſumed by little and little, with a ſlow &amp; lingring fire; and therfore the Officers were ſtill ready at hand to quench the flame when it bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned too faſt, for feare of diſpatching them too ſoone.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6944:9"/>
            <p>But for what end did they this? For no other ſurely, but that ſuch as would forſake their faith, and woorſhip their falſe Gods, might the more eaſily eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. And for this purpoſe alſo they left their bands ſo ſlacke, that they might themſelues eaſily vntye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and he that would yeild to the Preſidents offer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, might therby ſaue his life. And for the ſame cauſe likewiſe they ſet the gate of the place of Executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wide open, that whoſoeuer would, might caſt downe his crowne of Martyrdome, and eſcape both fire and ſword.</p>
            <p>But there was not found one amongſt all theſe Glorious Confeſſours, who did not in the very mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the ſcorching flames reioyce and triumph in our Lord: Who did not fixe his eyes vpon Heauen, with all hope and confidence in God: and who did not finally indure the burning fire with a quiet and cheerfull heart, and with his whole body ſo immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ac ſi dura ſilex, vel ſtet Marpeſia cautes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As if he had byn as hard as flint,</l>
                     <l>Which Iron cannot feele;</l>
                     <l>Or harder then Marpeſian rockes,</l>
                     <l>That blunt the ſharpeſt ſteele.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Neither was it for any ſhort tyme, that this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Conſtancy of the valiant Champions, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſtill inuincible, and vndaunted in the middeſt of the raging flames: For there wanted not ſome (whoſe diligence is greatly to be commended) who hauing of purpoſe brought hower-glaſſes with them, to note the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6944:10"/> tyme, affirme, that moſt of theſe holy Martyrs endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with incredible courage and magnanimity, this horrible torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for the ſpace of an hower and a halfe, and ſome others for the ſpace of two whole howers. Nay (which is more) concerning the bleſſed Martyr <hi>F. Sebastian Quimura</hi> of the Society of IESVS, they do conſtantly report, that they ſaw him broyling aliue in the fire for the ſpace of three whole howers, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noted by the hower-glaſſes, to the wonderfull aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Barbarous Gentils, who for many dayes after did talke of nothing elſe, but of this holy Martyrs ſo long ſufferance, &amp; that not without great wonder, and admiration.</p>
            <p>One thing there was, that amongſt the reſt, was a chiefe and ſpeciall cauſe of the great courage and conſtancy of theſe noble Champions, I meane the ſo extraordinary and great concourſe of Chriſtians that were preſent, which could not chooſe but be ſo much the greater, by how much they had notice of the time &amp; place long before, by meanes aſwell of the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as alſo in regard of the deſire they had to ſee ſo many famous Religious men, both of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponia,</hi> and ſuch venerable Prieſts, who had ſo long laboured and taken paines in the Vineyard of <hi>Iaponia,</hi> ſome for twenty, ſome for twenty fiue, yea and ſome for whole thirty yeares togeather.</p>
            <p>But that we may make ſome gheſſe at the number of the ſpectatours, it will not be amiſſe to call to mind what Father <hi>Iohn Baptista de Baeza</hi> of the Society of IESVS, Rectour of <hi>Nangaſachi,</hi> who hath dwelt in <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponia</hi> now full foure and thirty yeares, doth teſtify in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6944:10"/> his Letters ſent from thence to <hi>Manila,</hi> that there were to be found in that one only Citty of <hi>Nangaſachi,</hi> and in the Territory of the ſame, aboue fifty thouſand Chriſtians: ſo as there were preſent an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſaid Chriſtians, to ſee, and with great ioy and comfort to behold, how cheerfully theſe holy Martyrs all ended their liues in the midſt of burning flames; and how ſome of them as they were moſt pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully broyling, humbly falling vpon their knees, dyed moſt ſweetly, imbracing and kiſſing their ſtakes which now togeather with the Martyrs, were halfe conſumed by the fire.</p>
            <p>The fire was no ſooner out, but the Chriſtians inſtantly with great violence brake into the place of Execution, to reuerence and gather vp the ſacred Reliques. The Barbarous Guard bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at firſt to oppoſe themſelues againſt them, laying about them as hard as they could with their weapons: but when they ſaw they could not preuaile by this meanes, they inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted another, that therby both themſelues might ſeeme to depart with victory from the holy Bodyes; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that there ſhould not remaine the leaſt iote, or ſigne of the ſacred Reliques, in memory of the Martyrs.</p>
            <p>The Preſident therfore commanded a huge deepe pit to be made in the ground, and in the ſame a very great fire of wood, and all the bodies of the bleſſed Martyrs, togeather with the pillars and ſtakes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they had byn tyed, to be caſt into the ſame, and there burnt to aſhes, and laſtly all the aſhes very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put in ſackes to be carryed in ſhips farre out of the ſight of <hi>Nangaſachi,</hi> and there to be ſcattered,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6944:11"/> and caſt into the mayne ſea.</p>
            <p>The day next enſuing after this moſt illuſtrious Martyrdome, which was the eleauenth of September, was beheaded <hi>M. Gaſpar Cotengan-doxico,</hi> who was wont to accompany Father <hi>Camillus Conſtantius</hi> of the Society of IESVS, the Apoſtle of <hi>Iaponia;</hi> and who by trauailing vp and downe diuers parts of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try did greatly aſſiſt him in the conuerſion of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels. There were alſo beheaded with him two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that were the ſonnes of Martyrs, one wherof was but ſeauen, the other a little aboue nine yeares old.</p>
            <p>Another Chriſtian alſo as he was gathering vp ſome ſmall Reliques or aſhes of the ſacred bodyes of the burned Martyrs, which were kept with watch &amp; ward, within the forſaid place of Execution, was in the night apprehended, and brought before the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour; Who when he vnderſtood that he was a Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen of <hi>Omura,</hi> ſent him thither preſently as priſoner, where the Gouernour of that Citty, as ſoone as he arriued, put both him, and all his family to death; and ſo for the fayth of Chriſt they all obtayned a crowne of Martyrdome.</p>
            <p>The twelfth day of September there was at <hi>Omu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> a famous Martyrdome of the R. Father <hi>Thomas de Summarega,</hi> one of the moſt auncient amongſt thoſe of <hi>S. Dominick</hi> Order, that had laboured in the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of <hi>Iaponia;</hi> and of the R. Father <hi>Apollinaris Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> none of the laſt, or leaſt of the <hi>Iaponian</hi> Apoſtles, of the Order of <hi>S. Francis;</hi> and alſo of diuers other Iaponians, who were all conſumed by fire, for the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6944:11"/> fayth and loue of IESVS Chriſt. Amongſt theſe was a certaine Woman whoſe admirable piety and deuotion deſerueth euerlaſting memory: for that after ſhe had beene found by the Officers amongſt the ſacred Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of the fornamed holy Martyrs, and had already giuen ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimony, both by praying &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her ſelfe to their merits, what ſhe was; being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what ſhe was doyng, &amp; whether ſhe were a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or no, anſwered very couragiouſly, that they might eaſily ſee, if they had eyes, by what ſhe did, that ſhe was a Chriſtian. And what, (ſaid ſhe) will you haue any thing elſe with me? For this her reſolute an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere they made no more a doe, but inſtantly in the ſame place cut off her head, and caſt her body vpon the heape of the reſt of the Martyrs, which together with hers, do in all make the number of fifteene more.</p>
            <p>Ten other holy Martyrs alſo, togeather with <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine Onda</hi> of the Society of IESVS, who were all companions to Father <hi>Camillus Constantius</hi> of the ſame Society, were put to death at <hi>Yquinotima,</hi> a Towne of <hi>Iaponia</hi> nere vnto <hi>Firandum,</hi> for the fayth of Chriſt, being all burned aliue, and conſumed to aſhes.</p>
            <p>But the happy death of Father <hi>Camillus</hi> fell vpon the fifteenth day of September at <hi>Firandum,</hi> who there obteined a Crowne of Glory, ending the courſe of his Martyrdome by fire: where the concourſe of people was exceeding great, by reaſon that there were then lying in the Hauen at anker by <hi>Firandum,</hi> thirteene Engliſh and Holland ſhips well fraught with mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, and conſequently no ſmall ſtore of paſſengers, Marriners, ſouldiers, factours, and the like, that came
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6944:12"/> to ſee this ſaid ſpectacle. Father <hi>Camillus</hi> was an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> borne in <hi>Romagnia,</hi> who could ſpeake the Flemiſh tongue well, and diuers other languages beſides. He was a man of an Apoſtolicall ſpirit, of which he gaue ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimony by preaching in diuers Countries, wherby he greatly moued the peoples hearts, aſwell by reaſon of his rare Eloquence, as of the vehement feruour of his deuotion. In this Amphitheater where he was to be conſumed by fire, from out the pile of wood, as from ſome chaire or pulpit, he made a ſpeach vnto all the ſpectatours. But the Epilogue, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion therof he conuerted vnto the <hi>Iaponians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alone, of whoſe cuſtomes and ceremonies he had got no ſmall knowledge: in which he moſt effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly proued, and concluded, that the fayth of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS Chriſt was both true, neceſſary, and ſecure. And whilſt be ſpake thus, he did ſo rauiſh the <hi>Iaponians</hi> hearts with the ſweet harmony of his Eloquence, that they would not ſuffer the fire to be kindled ſo ſoone, as otherwiſe it ſhould haue byn, that they might not be ſo ſoone depriued of that ſweet fruite of his diuine ſpeach. Neyther was the heat of the fire able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come that heat of Charity which burned within his breſt. For euen after that the wood was all ſet on fire round about him, he ſtill caſt out fiery words on euery ſide vnto all the beholders, and could neuer make an end of ſpeaking, vntill he made an end of liuing.</p>
            <p>The ſecond day of October, Nine other noble Martyrs illuſtrated the Citty of <hi>Nangaſachi</hi> with their glorious deathes, wherof three little children died ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for the fayth of Chriſt. But that which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6944:12"/> to one of the nine is admirable to recount: For being in moſt cruell manner tortured for the ſpace of ſeauen dayes vpon the Racke, becauſe he refuſed to betray, and diſcouer certaine Religious men: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their racking, they were not able to wreſt from him any other words then <hi>Ieſus Maria, O Ieſus Maria! O what an ardent and burning deſire haue I to enter into the Glory of my Ieſus!</hi> with ſuch other like exclamations. So as the Executioners now perceiuing on the one ſide, that they laboured in vaine, and on the other ſide, being aſhamed to acknowledge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ouercome by a Chriſtian, they opened (O moſt barbarous or rather inhumane cruelty!) they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, I ſay, a hole in the fleſh of his ſhoulder, and therin poured boyling lead: Notwithſtanding all this, the valiant Champion of IESVS Chriſt remained ſtill ſo inuincible, that the Executioners quite deſpayring of the victory, with all rage and fury caſt him, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther withall his family, into the fire, and when there was nothing elſe of them left but aſhes, they gathered them vp, and threw it into the ſea.</p>
            <p>The 23. of September fiue other Chriſtians did conſecrate their liues to God, for hauing entertained and hidden in their houſes, the holy Martyr, Father <hi>Hyacinthus</hi> a Religious man of the Order of <hi>S. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke,</hi> wherof three, to wit, the husband, his wife, and their Child, were burned, and the other two behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>The 27. day of May, fower miles from <hi>Firan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> two other Chriſtians were put to death for the loue of IESVS Chriſt; the one for hauing lodged Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6944:13"/> 
               <hi>Camillus</hi> in his houſe, the other for hauing carryed him in his Barke to diuers places, to and fro, to preach the holy Ghoſpell of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Not long after this, happened a moſt rare Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome of a very Venerable man of foureſcore and fiue yeares old. This man was caſt headlong into the ſea, hauing tyed vnto his feet two ſo huge great ſtones, that one of them would haue bene inough to load foure luſty ſtrong fellowes; who inſtantly, and as it were in the twinckling of an eye ſunke downe to the very bottome: but behold a very ſtrang thing, as if both he, and the two great ſtones alſo had beene made of the lighteſt Corke, he came gliding vp againe to the very top, where ſwimming aboue the water, like the ſwan he began to ſing before his death, and with a moſt ſweet &amp; pleaſant voice, he repeated thrice this mellifluous ditty <hi>Ieſus Maria, Ieſus Maria, Ieſus Maria,</hi> and then by the weight of the ſtoones being drawne downe againe into the ſea, neuer appeared more.</p>
            <p>This Miraculous ſight and Martyrdome fell v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the 2. of Iune, to the great admiration of all the beholders, and particular ioy and comfort of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Chriſtians, that were preſent, and did ſee the ſame.</p>
            <p>Vpon the next day after, which was the 3. of Iune another Chriſtian man, and companion of Father <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millus Constantius</hi> of the Society of IESVS, was likewiſe put to death, for hauing aſſiſted him in Eccleſiaſtical functions and miniſteries. And vpon the 8. day of the ſame Moneth, another alſo ſuffered death, for the ſame cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6944:13"/>
            <p>Vpon the 28, of Iuly were three other Chriſtians, put to death, for a very ſtrange cauſe: for that (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) they would not lend their horſes to carry the holy Martyrs to execution; for indeed the Chriſtians did piouſly belieue, and perſuade themſelues, that it was a ſinne for any of them, ſo lend his horſe to help forward the execution of ſo barbarous a Cruelty.</p>
            <p>Two others alſo, that were Twinnes by birth, were put to a cruell Martyrdome, only for animating and encouraging of other Martyrs, that were ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hand to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with death in a grieuous agony. And another likewiſe, in another place, was crowned with Martyrdome for refuſing to lend his horſe to carry the Martyrs to their death.</p>
            <p>Neyther is he to be paſſed ouer with ſilence, who though his Name, and the manner of his Martyrdome in particuler be not knowne, yet was he put to death for the fayth of Chriſt in the Suburbes of a little town neere vnto <hi>Firandum,</hi> where certaine Husbandmen haue a few cottages for their habitation.</p>
            <p>This moſt illuſtrious and glorious Combat of purpled Martyrs, died in their owne bloud, ſhall be cloſed vp and concluded with the death of that renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Apoſtle of IESVS Chriſt, the R. Father <hi>Paulus Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarrus</hi> of the Society of IESVS, whoſe memory in <hi>Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> will liue for euer, where himſelf gaue his life for his flocke which he had for the ſpace of 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yeares, like a good Sheepheard moſt carefully fed, &amp; amongſt ſo many rauenous wolues moſt ſtoutly defended. He was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned to be burned aliue for hauing come out of <hi>Europe</hi> into <hi>Iaponta,</hi> againſt the Emperours lawes, to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6944:14"/> preach the Chriſtian fayth, therby to ouerthrow the worſhip of their Idols, and falſe Gods. When he had receiued this ſentence, all repleniſhed with ioy and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, he was brought vnto the ſtake, or pillar; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to after he was bound, and the fire kinded about him, he began to preach IESVS Chriſt with his Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall ſpirit, and ſo continued euen vnto the laſt gaſpe, when he rendred his bleſſed and pure Soule into the hands of his Creatour, and receiued the Crowne of his glorious Martyrdome, vpon the firſt day of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember, and feaſt of All-Saints.</p>
            <p>Neyther did he enioy this happy Crowne alone, but had for his Companions, and fellow-ſouldiers in Chriſt IESVS, two Brothers of the ſame Society of IESVS, to wit, <hi>Dennis,</hi> and <hi>Peter Sandaye:</hi> from whoſe company we muſt in no caſe exclude another Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that was both companion and guide to Father <hi>Paulus Nauarrus,</hi> to direct him the way vp and downe the country, and therfore deſerued in like manner to be made worthy of his bleſſed death, in requitall of his kindneſſe, and togeather with him, to obtaine a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Crowne of Martyrdome.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
               <p>Farewell! Adieu moſt noble Champions! Let them who dye th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue for euer! Let them triumph, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſay, liue: let them triumph for all Eternity! Let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce! This Glorious Tragedy is ended? What applauſe can be ſufficient for ſuch Noble Actes? for ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Scenes, as you haue heard? An hundred
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6944:14"/> and eighteene moſt ſweet Holocauſts ſacrificed for the loue of Chriſt, whereof fourty and ſix were offered vp by fire, all the reſt by ſword! O happy Soules! I honour you all. I reuerence your ſacred Names &amp; Memory: but eſpecially you, (you I meane) who being deuout Religious men, and of ſo many Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Families, to wit, of <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> one, of <hi>S. Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> fiue, of <hi>S. Dominicks</hi> ten, and of the Society of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS fourteene, haue thus manured, &amp; tilled the Iapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian barren ſoyle by your great labours; and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watered the ſame, with the ſweat of your deareſt Bloud!</p>
               <p>Many other notable things haue happened in the Martyrdome of theſe glorious Saintes, which we hope will very ſhortly come to light. In the meane tyme, read here the ſumme of what we haue receiued from vndoubted Authority. Almighty God in the booke of life, hath no doubt, made another reckoning. He hath ſet downe the number, not only of their heads, but euen of the leaſt hayres therof, though now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to aſhes. He (I ſay) hath ſet them downe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he meaneth to crowne them. We prayſe thee, O God, who art ſo glorious in thy Saints. We beſeech thee, Sweet IESVS, vouchſafe to make vs partakers of ſo glorious a Triumph. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:6944:15"/>
               <head>GENTLE READER.</head>
               <p>This former Relation, or briefe History, was wrytten from <hi>Nangaſachi</hi> and <hi>Firandum</hi> (two principall Citties of <hi>Iaponia,</hi> where moſt of the foreſaid Chriſtians ſuffered death) vnto <hi>Manila,</hi> the Chiefe Citty of the <hi>Philippine</hi> Ilands, by ſuch as were preſent at the Martyrdoms themſelues; and from thence very authentically ſent into <hi>Spaine,</hi> to diuers perſons there of Credit and Authority: VVhere the ſame was firſt published in print at <hi>Madrid,</hi> &amp; afterward at <hi>Seuill,</hi> &amp; other places; and ſince tranſlated into Latin, and printed at <hi>Bruxells</hi> in <hi>Brabant;</hi> and alſo into French, and printed in diuers Citties, both of <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countreyes,</hi> with licence and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, requiſite for the Truth of ſo notable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable an Accident.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:6944:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>S. IGNATIVS HIS TRIVMPH. OR</hi> A briefe Relation of ſome of the many Miracles, which God hath pleaſed to worke at <hi>Mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brega</hi> a Towne belonging to the Territory of the Citty of <hi>Calatayude,</hi> in the Kingdome of <hi>Arragon</hi> in <hi>Spayne,</hi> by the merits &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion of <hi>S. IGNATIVS de Loyola,</hi> Founder of the Society of <hi>IESVS,</hi> in the Moneths of April and May, of the yeare <hi>M.DC.XXIII.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>PON the 17. day Aprill, in the yeare of our Lord 1623. which fell out to be Munday in Eaſter Weeke, Father <hi>Valerius Piquer</hi> of the Society of IEEVS, after he had preached the whole Lent in <hi>Munebrega,</hi> a towne belonging to the Commandry and Libertyes of <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayude,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:6944:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6944:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:6944:17"/> a Citty of <hi>Arragon</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and ſcituate two Leagues diſtant thence; propoſed to the people, and deſired, that a certaine Picture of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> which then ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged priuately in the Sacriſty, or Veſtry of that Church, might be more publikely expoſed vpon ſome Altar, where Maſſes might be ſaid, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple pray, and doe their deuotions before it.</p>
            <p>So iuſt a petition being condeſcended vnto, the Vicar, and the Cleargy of that Pariſh Church, with the aſſiſtance of the greater part of the Inhabitants, Euenſong being ended, after the ſolemneſt manner they could, remoued, and placed the ſaid picture of <hi>S. Ignatius de Loyola</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an altar dedicated to <hi>S. Blaſe;</hi> &amp; hauing ſong the Ant-Hymne, and Prayer of <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> Father <hi>Piquer</hi> aforeſaid, made a Sermon for the ſpace of an hower, in honour and praiſe of the Saint, and therin recounted ſome of the Miracles, which by his interceſſion God had vouchſafed to ſhew in diuers places of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon this, a Vertuous and Venerable Matrone called <hi>Mary Guaſcon,</hi> of the age of 50. yeares, wife to <hi>Hierome Ladron de Gueuara,</hi> dwellers of the ſame town of <hi>Munebrega,</hi> who was ſo lame of one leg that ſhe could not go a ſtep, without the help of ſome other perſon to aſſiſt her, hearing of the miracles which the forſaid Father had recounted in his Sermon, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her ſelfe to <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> in the beſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner ſhe could, imploring ayd of Almighty God, through the merits and interceſſion of the Saint; and ſuddainly feeling a heauines to come vpon her, fell into a quiet ſlumber, &amp; by &amp; by awaking, found her ſelfe well &amp; ſound, &amp;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6944:17"/> the lameneſſe of her Leg wholy departed from her. At which ſhe greatly reioyced, and forthwith went without any help, or ſtay of any, towards the Church, to giue God, and <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> thankes for her deliuery from that infirmity, to the great admiration and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all that dwelled in the towne, who knew full well her long and troubleſome lameneſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame day, <hi>Mary Pariente</hi> wife to <hi>Alonſo Bueſſo,</hi> who hauing no vſe at all of her left arme, after ſhe had ſought and applied many remedies without any good ſucceſſe, but rather greater harme, ſeing that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of curing her, the Chirurgeons had broken the bone of her arme, &amp; that the Phiſitians had now aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned her as one deſperate &amp; incurable: And calling to mind what had paſſed with <hi>Mary Guaſcon</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, prayed thus deuoutly into the Saint: O bleſſed <hi>Ignatius,</hi> if God through thy merits, would be pleaſed to cure me, I would ſhew forth his praiſes and thine, to my vttermoſt power. And euen at that inſtant, ſhe felt in her left arme, a great conuulſion of the bones and ſynewes, and preſently after found her ſelfe well, and her arme perfectly recouered. Wherfore with a loud voyce ſhe vttered theſe words, <hi>I am whole, and cured by the fauour and merits of S. Ignatius:</hi> and ſhe ſtirred vp and downe her arme, as if it had neuer bene any way annoyed before.</p>
            <p>Within a while after <hi>Mary Santijus</hi> wife to <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Bueno de la Muda,</hi> who being almoſt blind, and could only diſcerne but the bulkes of bodies, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing any perſon; comming to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell where the foreſaid picture was newly ſet vp,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6944:18"/> made her prayer, ſaying: O holy <hi>Ignatius</hi> obtayne for me, I humbly beſeech thee, my perfect ſight, if it ſhall pleaſe Almighty God; and I heere faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to procure a Maſſe to be ſaid at thy Altar, in ſigne of gratitude and thankefulnes. At that very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant it ſeemed to her, that her eyes gaue a turne in her head, &amp; ſhe remained with a cleare ſight, knowing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and perfectly all that were preſent, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth ſtill, enioying this benefit and fauour, which God, for <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> ſake, hath granted vnto her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bernardina Benedid</hi> of the age of 31. yeares, wife to <hi>Philip Gomez,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Munebrega,</hi> had for the ſpace of eight yeares bene torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with diuers diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as hauing one vlcer in the liuer, and another in the ſpleene, togeather which a defluction from the Head to the Lungs; and ſometimes alſo there grew a kind of impoſtume in her ſtomacke, which breaking made her vomite much putrified matter, and bloud; by which meanes ſhe came to haue ſo great weakenes and debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of ſtomacke, that for ſix yeares togeather ſhe could not retaine any kind of meate, but was fayne preſently to caſt all vp againe; &amp; whenſoeuer ſhe vſed any force to hold it in, it would breake through her noſtrills: &amp; in caſe there remained any thing behind, cleauing to ſome parts of the ſtomacke, it bred ſuch ſtore of bloud, that neceſſarily she was driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be let bloud twice or thrice euery other moneth, for feare of being choaked; by which meanes alſo ſhe fell many tymes into fits of ſwoundings, and at laſt was brought ſo low and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that ſhe ſeemed nothing els but skin and bones, being vnable either to ſtirre her ſelfe, or ſuffer that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6944:18"/> ſhould ſo much as touch her, for feare of increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her great paines. Now by reaſon of theſe ſo many and grieuous indiſpoſitions of her body, the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians and Chirurgeons, after diuers Conſultations had about her, gaue her ouer for incurable. At which <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Gomez</hi> her ſonne, much grieuing and lamenting his mothers pittifull caſe, told her, that he would carry her to the Church where <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> had wrought ſo great miracles: and her husband being by, byd her offer 9. Maſſes to be ſaid there in his honour. She an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that, that was euen to carry her thence to her graue, by reaſon of her weakenes. Preſently after came in Father <hi>Valerius Piquer,</hi> &amp; ſayd vnto her: Haue confidence in God, and in his Saint: and withall gaue vnto her a Relique of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> which ſhe reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with much deuotion, beſeeching him to obtayne health for her at the hands of God Almighty. Vpon this ſhe fell into a ſwound, and extraordinary ſweate: but when ſhe came to her ſelfe againe, ſhe cryed out; I find my ſelfe throughly well, let me go to the Saints Picture in the Church. And within halfe an houre af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (for before ſhe could not get away from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which came ſo faſt into the houſe to ſee her) ſhe roſe vp from her bed well and ſtrong, and went alone downe the ſtayres: but the people not permitting her to go any further a foote, would needes carry her to the Church doore in a chaire, from whence ſhe went her ſelfe on foote to the Chappell, and gaue thankes to God, and to <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after ſhe had ended her prayer, ſhe returned home to her own houſe a foote, &amp; ſupped with the reſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6944:19"/> of her family, like vnto one that was in as perfect health as any of the reſt, without changing any thing afterward of the common dyet of the houſe, or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any indiſpoſition euen vnto this preſent day. The next day after ſhe went againe to the Church, where ſhe made her Confeſſion and receiued the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with great deuotion and thanksgiuing, ſtill remaning in good health &amp; perfect ſtrength of body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſchalis Gabrerizo</hi> an honeſt poore inhabitant of <hi>Munebrega</hi> had bene for the ſpace of 12 yeares diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo benummed in his feet, that he was not able to go without one crutch at leaſt; beſides, he had no vſe of one of his armes, and did almoſt continually ſuffer extreame paine of the Goute, togeather with a great palpitation of the hart. He now ſeing the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> had wrought, with deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer his former health, conceiued great deuotion to the Saint, and hauing made vp a Ryall in money, which he had gotten by almes of good people, (for he was very poore) procured therwith a Maſſe to be ſaid at the Altar of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> whereat he was preſent, &amp; deuoutly recommended himſelfe to God and the Saint with great confidence of his recouery. The Maſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, he roſe vp with his Crutch to go backe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his houſe, and at the Church doore he found himſelfe wel, and free from the lameneſſe of his leggs: ſo as caſting away his Crutch, he very nimbly and ſpeedily went vp and downe, praiſing God and <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> for the cure; nor was he only cured of his feet, but alſo of his arme, and of the troubleſome paſſion of his Hart. This miracle was ſo publicke &amp; notorious to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6944:19"/> all the towne of <hi>Munebrega,</hi> that moſt of the people lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their ſhops and houſes repayred and flocked to the Church to admire the ſucceſſe; and the poore man was there found amongſt them giuing thanks to God and the Saint: in whoſe Chappell he hanged vp his Crutch for a perpetuall memory.</p>
            <p>A little child called <hi>Mary Pardo</hi> daughter to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minike Pardo,</hi> and <hi>Magdalene Ximeno,</hi> dwellers of <hi>Mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brega,</hi> had ſome two yeares before fallen into the fire, and burnt her left arme, eſpecially about the Elbow, wherby the ſynewes were dryed &amp; ſhrunke vp in ſuch ſort, that ſhe had no vſe at all of that arme. <hi>Peter de Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> a Religious man of <hi>S. Augustines</hi> Order, &amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelour of Diuinity, came to the houſe, and annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the childs arme with ſome of the oile of the Lampe that burned before the picture of <hi>Saint Ignatius</hi> in his Chappell; which being done and the Girle feeling her arme a little more pliable then before, he willed her mother to annoynt it daily wherwith; which as ſhe was doyng the next day, ſhe ſayd: Daughter lift vp thy arme; and at the inſtant ſhe heard as it were a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ruſhing of the bones togeather, &amp; perceiued that the arme grew ſomewhat greater, &amp; amended; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon continuing to annoint it, after the ſame manner, ſome two or three dayes more, her daughter was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Corriz,</hi> wife to <hi>Pedro Bueno</hi> dwelling in the towne of <hi>Munebrega,</hi> hauing a foule Canker in one of her legs wherby ſhe was in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to haue it cut off, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Maſſe to be ſaid at the Altar of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> and there annoynting the diſeaſed part, with the oyle of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6944:20"/> his Lampe, the Canker was healed, and leauing there behind her the Crutch which before ſhe vſed, ſhe ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully returned home.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Mun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oz</hi> wife of <hi>Michael Marina,</hi> inhabitants of <hi>Vijueſca,</hi> had one of her Legs ſo dried vp and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed away, that ſhe could not ſtirre or mooue the ſame. The Phiſitians deſpairing of all humane reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, her friends would needs conuay her to <hi>Belmonte,</hi> to a famous Chirurgeon of that place. He looking vpon, and conſidering well the diſeaſed part, ſaid, that there was no meanes poſſible to cure it; &amp; that it were good ſhe recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded her ſelfe to <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> who wrought ſo many miracles at <hi>Munebrega;</hi> for other humane help ſhe might aſſure her ſelfe there was none. The good woman followed the Chirurgeons counſayle, &amp; went to <hi>Munebrega</hi> to viſit the Chappell of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> where hearing Maſſe, &amp; recommending her ſelfe with great deuotion to the glorious Saint, preſently found her ſelfe free from her diſeaſe, and was able to go her iourney backe on foot, to her owne houſe at <hi>Vijueſca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was another woman in <hi>Munebrega,</hi> a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and very poore, who had a grieuous ſoare in her right foote, and both her legs greatly ſwollen, which made her perforce go with crutches. Being thus priuy to her owne miſery and affliction, &amp; ſeing the wonders which God did worke by meanes of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> ſhe went to his Picture, &amp; reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended her ſelfe very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly vnto him; &amp; before ſhe departed the Church, ſhe recouered her perfect health, and left there her Crutches, being very well able to walke home a foot. But firſt of all ſhe forgot not to render her beſt thankes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6944:20"/> vnto God, and the Saint for ſo ſingular a benefit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Agnes Cauallero</hi> wife to <hi>Martin de Huerta</hi> Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Nueualo,</hi> being blind, in ſuch manner as that ſhe could not go a ſtep without a guide, hauing alſo a foule Canker growing ouer one of her lips; and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the miracles which <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> wrought, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to go to <hi>Munebrega,</hi> to viſit his Chappell, and pray vnto him for remedy of theſe her infirmities. She was led thither, &amp; for the ſpace of 3. dayes made conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall prayer with great deuotion and confidence in his Chappell, &amp; annoynting her lip and eyes with the oile of the Lampe that burned before his Altar, obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perfect recouery both of her lippe &amp; eyes; &amp; euer ſince her eye-ſight hath bene ſo good, as ſhe is able to threed a very ſmall needle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antony Franco</hi> inhabitant of <hi>Castejon</hi> vpon <hi>Alarua</hi> in <hi>Caſtile,</hi> hauing bene abroad, came home to his houſe with a burning feuer on his backe, and an impoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me alſo, riſen through heate, in his ſtomacke, which cauſed him extreme payne. The Phiſitian came vnto him, and ſeing that his ſicknes was mortall, bad him diſpoſe of his ſoule, and temporall eſtate, for he could not aſſure him aboue twelue houres of life. Now the fame of the miracles which our Lord had wrought by the interceſſion of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> in <hi>Munebrega</hi> being ſpred abroad far &amp; neere, &amp; come vnto this place; the friends of the ſicke Patient, fomented his ſtomacke with ſome of the oyle which they had gotten of the Lampe that burned in the Chappel of the Saint at <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrega</hi> aforeſaid: and the ſicke man himſelfe, with all the reſt inuocating <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> for ayde with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6944:21"/> in a moment he felt himſelfe fully well, and forthwith, in all gratitude and affection, aroſe and went to <hi>Munebrega</hi> on pilgrimage, to giue God tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, at the Chappell of the Saint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Franciſa Locano,</hi> wife of <hi>Dominicke Marco</hi> Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of <hi>Valtorres,</hi> who hauing one of her breſts greatly ſwolne with two great hard bunches, which made her often fall into a ſwounding; vpon the fame of theſe miracles, reſolued to viſite the Chappell of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> and to recommend herſelfe vnto him with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, although ſhe had receiued the Sacrament of Extreme Vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but three dayes before. Being brought therefore to <hi>Munebrega,</hi> and recommending her ſelfe in moſt deuout manner vnto the glorious Saint in his Chappell, preſently her breſt began to ſweat, with much eaſe of her payne, and ſo continuing to viſit the Chappell for 9. dayes together, ſhe found, at laſt, her ſelfe prefectly cured of the foreſaid ſwellings, and the colour of the ſweat of her breſts turned into the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of bloud. She had endured the payne and trouble of this diſeaſe for nine yeares continually; and now at laſt through the merits of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> receiued perfect cure and remedy, by her prayers and deuotions of nine dayes, which ſhe daily powred out before his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar; and ſo came ioyfully home to her owne houſe at <hi>Valtorres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matthew Pola,</hi> of the age of 20. yeares inhabitant of <hi>Ateca,</hi> hauing a continuall palſy in one of his armes and legs, being not able to mooue, or ſerue himſelfe with eyther of them in any occaſion; cauſed himſelfe to be conueyed to <hi>Munebrega</hi> with great confidence to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6944:21"/> obtaine remedy by the mediation and merits of <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius.</hi> When he arriued thither, for nine dayes ſpace togeather, with much deuotion, he determined, and began to annoynt euery day his legge and arme with ſome of the oile of the lampe that burned before <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> Altar; but vpon the eight day he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſound, and ſo perfectly recouered, as if he had bene neuer troubled at al in thoſe parts of his body with any infirmity whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Garzia</hi> Inhabitant of <hi>Tortuera,</hi> an old man of the age of 74. yeares, had ſo great an impediment in his tongue, that he could not ſcarce pronounce one word perfectly to be vnderſtood. Hearing others make mention of the miracles which <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> did worke at <hi>Munebrega;</hi> he went thither in all laſt to viſite his Chappell, and recommending himſelfe very earneſtly and deuoutly vnto his merits, and annoynting his tongue with the oile of the lampe aforeſaid, ſpake very cleerly and diſtinctly, and ſo continueth to this day, through the Goodnes of God, and interceſſion of the Bleſſed Saint.</p>
            <p>A certaine woman of the Citty of <hi>Calatayude,</hi> hauing ſuch a benumming in her hands, that they ſerued her to no vſe; and her leggs alſo being benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the ſame manner, would neyther beare her vp, nor ſuffer her ſo much as to kneele, did moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and deuoutly recommended her ſelfe to <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> at <hi>Munebrega,</hi> and without any other remedy ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered her entire and perfect health.</p>
            <p>Another woman, a wyddow of the ſame Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, hauing a daughter of ſome 6. or 7. yeares old, who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6944:22"/> by reaſon of a great weakeneſſe and other infirmityes in her leggs, was not able to go vp or downe any ſtayres; hearing of theſe miracles, and iudging that <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> liked well, that widdowes (according to the manner of <hi>Spaine</hi>) ſhould liue retired at home in their owne houſes, made this prayer vnto him, in a moſt effectuall manner: O glorious Saint, it doth not ſuite well with my ſtate of Widdowhood, to make iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes abroad, in the ſight of many people, no not although it be to go on pilgrimage to viſit your Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of <hi>Muncbrega;</hi> the power of Curing which you can do there, I doubt not, but that you are able alſo to worke heere; and the graces and fauours which you ſhew in that place abroad to others, you can as well ſhew in this, to my little daughter heere at home; Let it pleaſe you then (O bleſſed Saint) to cure her. A little after this her prayer, ſhe ſaw her daughter go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp and downe the ſtayres of the houſe ſo readily, as if ſhe had neuer had my impediment, or defect in her leggs before.</p>
            <p>A little ſonne of <hi>Don Iohn Perez</hi> of <hi>Nueros,</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by his Fathers Coach, which was ready at the doore for him to go abroad, &amp; playing with the wheels, the Mules vpon a ſuddaine began to run away with the Coach as being feared with ſomthing that paſſed in the ſtreet; &amp; ouerthrowing the boy vpon the ground, one of the wheels paſſed ouer the very middle of his face. A Gentlewoman which ſaw it, cryed out, and ſayd: <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaue the Child; and euen at that very inſtant the Mules ſtopt, and ſtood ſtill, &amp; drawing away the child, they found that he had
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6944:22"/> no other harme at all, but onely that the markes of the nayles were ſeene, which the wheeles had lightly left imprinted vpon his face.</p>
            <p>A Venerable Father of the Order of <hi>S. Francis,</hi> of the Monaſtery in <hi>Calatayude,</hi> who had byn lame, and gone halting a long tyme together, determined for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy therof to go on foote, by little and little, to <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrega,</hi> to viſit the Chappell of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi> He was ſcarce gone a quarter of a league with great paine and trouble, when he bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſtruſt of being able to paſſe any further, and ſo ſate himſelfe downe; and taking out his Breuiary, began to ſay his Mattins in honour of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> which when he had done, he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe animated and encouraged to proſecute the reſt of of his iourney. Going therfore forward, the more he went, the better he felt himſelfe, and when he came to <hi>Munebrega</hi> he found himſelfe wholy cured; ſo as giuing thankes in the Chappell of the Saint, he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe ioyfully, &amp; in very perfect health to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Pardos,</hi> a village of ſome 40. Houſes, a yong girle of twelue yeares of age, became ſo ſtopt vpon a ſuddaine with the increaſe of aboundance of bloud in the ſpring ſeaſon, that within a little tyme ſhe fell ſicke and dyed, and remayned foure houres dead and cold. Her mother much afflicted therewith, recommended her to <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> with ſo great fayth and perſeuerance, that all thoſe foure houres ſhe ceaſed not to beſeech the Saint, that by his merits, he would intreat of God, that her daughter might returne to life againe. <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> hard her prayer, and the Child returning to herſelfe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6944:23"/> ſayd vnto her mother; O mother, now I am well, <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> hath raiſed me vp from death, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me to preſent my ſelfe in his Chappell at <hi>Munc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brega;</hi> and ſo preſently ſhe was carryed thither, and the next day after ſent into the feild to keepe ſheepe, which ſhe was wont to do, by reaſon of her pouerty.</p>
            <p>The Phiſitian which dwelleth at this day in <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrega,</hi> had an Infant ſome 2. or 3. monthes old, that being fed with certaine ſops, was choaked on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and as his Father iudged, and ſince proteſted ſtarke dead, in ſo much that he gaue order for his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall; but the mother with more fayth and deuotion, annoynted her little babe with ſome of the oyle of the lampe of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> making deuout ſupplication to the Saint for the recouery of life againe in her ſonne, and therwith all ſhe offred him to <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi> At that very inſtant the child came againe to himſelfe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to cry, and by the fauour and merits of the Saint, continueth ſtill in perfect health.</p>
            <p>¶ This foreſaid Picture of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> which God Almighty hath made the meanes of ſo many, and ſo wonderfull miracles, ſome ſixteene yeares ſince was, by <hi>Don Rocque de Villar</hi> Chanon of <hi>Calatayude,</hi> firſt ſet vp in the Sacriſty, or Veſtry of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Munebrega,</hi> togeather with other Founders of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Orders amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the pictures of diuers Cardinals, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Maiſters of the Order of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>Malta,</hi> Vicechancellours, Iuſtices, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors of Eſtate, Iudges of his Catholike Maieſty, and of other worthy and famous Perſons, which had bene ſometimes promoted from this place to theſe dignities;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6944:23"/> and being compared with many other pictures of the ſame Saint, ſeemeth to differ from them all, as ſhewing, ſomewhat ſuperiour, and extraordinary, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty it carrieth in the Face.</p>
            <p>Vpon the firſt Friday, after it was placed vpon the Altar, being the 21. day of Aprill, hauing bene kept alwayes before in a dry place, it began to ſweat on the right ſide vnder the arme, and ſo continued for the ſpace of 4. howers; which ſweat was an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kind of liquor, much differing from water, although it ſeemed ſo in colour, as alſo from oyle, or any other running liquor; but it came out ſwelling, like certaine full &amp; thicke drops; and as faſt as it was dryed vp, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the ſame liquor began to flow out againe; all which was gathered, and drunke vp with two great linnen Towlls, and is yet there kept.</p>
            <p>Vpon Friday alſo a fortnight after, being the 5. of <hi>May,</hi> the ſame ſweat began againe to flow forth, for the ſpace of two houres. Witneſſes of theſe ſweatings were many Eccleſiaſticall, and Religious perſons, who ſaw them, &amp; the R. Father <hi>Friar Peter Villar</hi> of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and Bachelour of Diuinity, did wet two handkerchers therwith, which are kept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day.</p>
            <p>Some few dayes after, a certaine woman of the towne of <hi>Alarua,</hi> hauing heard of the miracles of <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> out of a deſire to find remedy againſt a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous great ſwelling which ſhe had in her breſts, to her extreme griefe and payne; came to <hi>Munebrega</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending her ſelfe deuoutly to the Saint, in his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, preſently ſhe felt certaine drops of water to run
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6944:24"/> downe her breaſt, as if it had bene ſome ſweat of that ſwelling, which much eaſed her paine, and which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to grow leſſe. Vpon this, one of the Towells wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſweat aforeſaid of the Picture had byn dryed vp, was applyed vnto her breſt, and the ſwelling pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently reſolued it ſelfe into great aboundance of water, &amp; by and by after the woman remained wholy cured.</p>
            <p>Many other famous miracles haue bene wrought there, by the Merits and Interceſſion of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> which do exceed the number of an hundred; all which haue byn wrought within the ſpace of one month, and are moſt notorious to all the Inhabitants therabout. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, beſides thoſe aboue mentioned, there haue byne foure blind reſtored to their ſight, many Cripples, many deafe, and many ſicke of diuers infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mityes perfectly cured. So that it would be ouer long to recount them all heere in this briefe Relation, ſince there ſcarce paſſeth any day, wherin ſome one miracle or other is not wrought, and ſome dayes three or foure. Therfore it is no meruaile if vpon the certaine fame of ſo many, and continuall miracles, there be ſo great concourſe of people, from all parts of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of <hi>Spaine,</hi> vnto this Chappell of <hi>S. Ignatius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo many Cittyes, Townes, and Villages do daily repaire thither in ſolemne Proceſſion; in ſo much that continually the Church of <hi>Munebrega</hi> is full of Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, ſome blind, ſome lame, ſome with vlcers, others with other diſeaſes, who daily through the merits and interceſſion of this glorious Saint do receiue health, and moſt ſingular fauours at the hands of God. And if the Church of <hi>Munebrega</hi> were ſix times larger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6944:24"/> (and it is of a reaſonable good bignes:) yet would it be too little for all commers, who ſtriue to be there early in the morning, yea, and many tymes remayne there all night, to occupy, and preuent the getting of a good and commodious place.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, it is iudged for a thing certaine, that there is no one holy Place or Pilgrimage throughout all <hi>Spaine,</hi> more frequented at this day, then is the forſaid Chappell of Saint Ignatius in <hi>Munebrega.</hi> Wherfore the ſayd towne of <hi>Munebrega</hi> hath choſen this Saint Ignatius, for their ſpeciall Patron, and vowed to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate his feaſt yearely with all ſolemnity poſſible. Alſo in <hi>Maluenda, Villaroy,</hi> and other places within the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts, and Territoryes of <hi>Calatayude,</hi> they haue lately dedicated diuers Chappells and Altars vnto <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> of Loyola, Founder of the Society of IESVS.</p>
            <p>That which moſt of all ought to be pondered, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this famous place of Pilgrimage, is the great fruite, and the notable conuerſions of many loſt and damnable ſoules, which vpon this occaſion hath byn wrought by generall Confeſſions; beſides the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full changes in many from moſt wicked and deſperate, vnto vertuous and godly liues. And without all doubt, this is that, which principally <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> pretendeth by the working of ſo great Miracles. For although in his life tyme, he alwayes exerciſed himſelfe in Corporall workes of Mercy; yet principally did he practiſe the Spirituall, with all poſſible endeauour, as moſt grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and pleaſing to the diuine Goodnes.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:6944:25"/>
               <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
               <p>This Relation hath bene gathered, and taken from many Examinations, and Depoſitions receiued authentically by an Apoſtolicall Notary, &amp; fiue others of the Kings Notaryes, in preſence of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of the Towne of <hi>Munebrega;</hi> and from the letters which the R. Father <hi>Peter Villar</hi> of the Order of <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> and Bachelour of Diuinity; Father <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome Alagre</hi> Rector of the College of the Society of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS in <hi>Calatayude;</hi> Father <hi>Valerius Piquer,</hi> and Father <hi>Francis Perez de Culla</hi> of the ſame Society, and diuers others, haue teſtified, and authentically wrytten to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny principall Perſons in <hi>Madrid:</hi> where this preſent Relation was firſt publiſhed, and printed by <hi>Lewis San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chez,</hi> Printer to his Catholike Maieſty, with ſpeciall Priuiledge.</p>
               <p>Let vs then be ſo happy, as not to want the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull interceſſion of this Glorious Saint, to the end we may not only obtaine at Gods hands, health and Commodities of the Body; but much more the Health, Saluation, and Eternall good of our Soules: &amp; let vs all deuoutly ſay with Holy Church, as followeth:</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:6944:25"/>
            <head>The Prayer of the Church, to S. Ignatius.</head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <p>DEus qui glorificantes te glorificas, &amp; in San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum tuorum honoribus honoraris; concede propitius: vt qui Sancti <hi>IGNATII</hi> Confeſſoris tui glorioſa merita colimus, eius pia patrocinia ſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Per Dominum noſtrum Ieſum Chriſtum filium tuum, qui tecum viuit &amp; regnat, in vnitate Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſancti Deus. Per omnia ſaecula ſaeculorum.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>IN ENGLISH.</head>
               <p>O God, who glorifieſt thoſe that glorify thee, &amp; art honoured in the Honours of thy Saints; Grant graciouſly, that we who reuerence the glorious merits of thy Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour S. IGNATIVS, may be made partakers of his pious Patronage. Through our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt thy Sonne, who liueth &amp; raigneth with thee, in vnity of the Holy Ghoſt, one God, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6944:26"/>
            <trailer>Laus Deo, B. Virgini Mariae, &amp; Sancto Ignatio.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6944:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
